<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
    $LastChangedRevision$
    $LastChangedDate$
-->

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR1/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="Preface" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Preface</title>
  <para>
    The monad concept is surrounded by mysticism among many programmers. It is poorly understood and its importance is
    widely under-appreciated. In this essay, I will attempt to provide a concrete understanding of the term and it will
    also explicitly address many of the common myths. I will also provide insight into the importance of the concept
    and why it should matter to you.
  </para>
  <para>
    A few different programming languages will be used; Java, C#, Haskell and Scala to name a few. This is because
    monads are totally unrelated to specific programming languages. Indeed, monads are prevalent to every
    turing-complete programming language. However, you are not expected to be intimate with the syntaxes of these
    various languages. Where there is possibility for the syntax to cause confusion, clarification will be provided.
  </para>
  <para>
    This essay will not use cute metaphors. Monads are not space-suits or any such notion that may confuse a reader. We
    will not go into the heavy mathematics behind monads (category theory), however, you will be expected to think
    somewhat abstractly at times, but only to an extent that you probably akin to.
  </para>
  <para>
    I intend to be thorough in debunking many of the misunderstandings and providing all the tools to help you
    understand this apparently elusive computer programming concept and its important application. It must be said that
    the concept does not deserve much of the attention that it receives and you will soon see why. I hope you enjoy this
    essay and it brings you enlightenment and adds to your tools to make you a more effective computer programming. If
    you have questions, feedback or criticism, please send it to the mailing list
    <email>monad-tutorial@googlegroups.com</email>.
  </para>
</sect1>
