<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
    $LastChangedRevision$
    $LastChangedDate$
-->

<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5CR1/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="NotMonad" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>¬Monad</title>
  <sect2>
    <title>Side-Effects</title>
    <para>
      It is a common misunderstanding that monads are all about side-effects, particularly in a pure functional
      programming language. It is true that monads can provide a mechanism for controlling side-effects, but this is
      only one instance of the use of monads.
    </para>
    <para>
      To draw an analogy, suppose you wrote a function to compute the length of a linked list. If you wrote this
      function responsibly, it would work on a list of any element type. In other words, the function would be
      <emphasis>polymorphic</emphasis>. You might use this function to compute the length of a list of
      <code>Banana</code> elements, but this would not be sufficient to say that your length function is in some way
      related to the <code>Banana</code> type.
    </para>
    <para>
      Just like you can compute the length of a list of <code>Banana</code> elements, it is also true that you can use
      monads to represent side-effects, but the relationship does not go any further. In other words, the relationship
      between monads and side-effects is incredibly weak at a stretch, but non-existent in practical terms. Later on,
      once we know what monad means, we will see a demonstration of how side-effects can be represented using monads. <!-- todo reference -->
    </para>
    <para>
      To fully appreciate this point, consider that monads are not specific to any particular programming language. For
      example, monads are relevant in a language that could not possibly be described as a
      <quote>pure functional programming language</quote>, such as Java. The next section will discuss this. <!-- todo reference -->
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Monads and Programming Languages</title>
    <para>
      TODO
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
